<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aula lucis, or, The house of light : a discourse written in the year 1651. / By S.N. a modern speculator.</title>
            <author>Vaughan, Thomas, 1622-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1367_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869512</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869512</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 254:E1367[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aula lucis, or, The house of light : a discourse written in the year 1651. / By S.N. a modern speculator.</title>
                  <author>Vaughan, Thomas, 1622-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 25 [i.e. 39], [13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for VVilliam Leake, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Crowne in Fleet-street, between the two Temple Gates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Vaughan by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>With final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 14. 1651."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Light --  Symbolic aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Aula Lucis, OR, The Houſe of LIGHT: A Diſcourſe written in the year 1651.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> S. N. <hi>a Modern Speculator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hic locus eſt, quem (ſi verbis audacia detur) Haud timeam magni dixiſſe palatia Coeli</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>vVilliam Leake,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the Crowne in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> between the two Temple Gates, 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:2"/>
            <head>To my beſt, and nobleſt Friend, <hi>Seleucus Abantiades.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat <hi>you are,</hi> I need not tell you: what <hi>I am,</hi> you know already. Our <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance</hi> began with my <hi>Child-hood,</hi> and now you ſee what a <hi>Peere</hi> you have purchaſed. I can partly refer my <hi>inclinations</hi> to your ſelf, and <hi>thoſe</hi> onely which I derive from the <hi>contemplative Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> for the <hi>reſt</hi> are beſides your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence.</hi> I here preſent you with the <hi>fruits</hi> of them, that you may ſee my <hi>Light</hi> hath <hi>Water</hi> to play withall. Hence it is, that I move in
<pb facs="tcp:170666:3"/>the <hi>Sphaere</hi> of <hi>Generation,</hi> and fall ſhort of that <hi>Teſt</hi> of <hi>Heraclitus, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Siccum optima Anima.</hi> I need not expound this to you, for you are in the <hi>Center,</hi> and ſee it. How ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you may excuſe me, if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Conceptions</hi> to <hi>Fancies;</hi> I could never <hi>affect</hi> any thing that was <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren;</hi> for <hi>Sterility</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent.</hi> Give me a <hi>knowledge</hi> that's <hi>fertile</hi> in <hi>performances,</hi> for <hi>Theories</hi> without their <hi>effects,</hi> are but <hi>Nothings</hi> in the <hi>dreſs</hi> of <hi>things.</hi> How <hi>true</hi> this is, you can <hi>tell me;</hi> and if I but <hi>recite</hi> what is your <hi>owne,</hi> you muſt not therefore <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue</hi> it, it being in ſome ſenſe a <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> for <hi>Men</hi> have <hi>nothing</hi> to <hi>give,</hi> but what they <hi>receive</hi> Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me then at the preſent to ſtand your <hi>Cenſer,</hi> and <hi>exhale</hi> that <hi>incenſe</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170666:3"/>which your <hi>owne Hands</hi> have put in I dare not ſay here is <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> nor can I boaſt with the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Artiſt</hi> you read of, that I have lived three yeares <hi>in Regione Lucis.</hi> It is enough that I have <hi>light,</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Perſia</hi> had his <hi>Sponſa Solis;</hi> and truly I thinke a <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> to have ſeene that <hi>Candle lodg'd,</hi> which our Fathers judg'd to be <hi>Lux errans, quaerens Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum.</hi> But I grow <hi>abſurd,</hi> I ſpeake as if I would <hi>inſtruct</hi> you; and now me thinks you aske me,
<q>Quis Legit Haec?</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is I Sir that read the <hi>Tactics</hi> here to <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and teach him to break <hi>Rocks</hi> with <hi>Vinacre.</hi> I am indeed ſomewhat <hi>Pedantic</hi> in this, but the <hi>libertie</hi> you are ſtill pleaſed to <hi>allow</hi> me, hath carried me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb facs="tcp:170666:4"/>my <hi>Cue.</hi> It is a <hi>treſpaſſe</hi> you know, that's very <hi>ordinary</hi> with me, and ſome junior <hi>Collegues:</hi> nor can I omit theſe <hi>Verſes</hi> which you have been ſometimes pleaſed to apply to this <hi>forwardneſſe</hi> of mine.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Talis Amyclaei domitus Pollucis habenis</l>
               <l>Cyllarus, &amp; quorum Graij meminere poetae,</l>
               <l>Martis equi bijuges, &amp; magni eurrus Achillis</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is my opinion Sir, that <hi>truth</hi> cannot be urg'd with too much <hi>ſpirit,</hi> ſo that I have not <hi>ſinned</hi> here as to the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelfe, for the <hi>dangers</hi> onely in your <hi>Perſon.</hi> I am affraid my <hi>boldneſſe</hi> hath been <hi>ſuch,</hi> I may be thought to fall ſhort of that <hi>Reverence</hi> I owe you. This is it indeed which I dare call a <hi>Sin,</hi> and I am ſo <hi>farre</hi> from <hi>it,</hi> that it is my <hi>private wonder,</hi> how I came
<pb facs="tcp:170666:4"/>to <hi>thinke it.</hi> Suffer me then to be <hi>impertinent</hi> for once; and give me leave to <hi>repent</hi> of an <hi>humour,</hi> which I am <hi>confident</hi> you place not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my <hi>faults,</hi> but amongſt your owne <hi>Indulgences.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant. <hi>S. N.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Heliopolis</hi> 
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:5"/>
            <head>To the preſent Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will be queſtioned perhaps by the <hi>envious,</hi> to what purpoſe theſe <hi>ſheets</hi> are <hi>proſtituted;</hi> and eſpecially that <hi>Drug</hi> wrapt in them, the <hi>Philoſophers Stone.</hi> To theſe it is anſwered by <hi>Solomon, There a is time to caſt away Stones:</hi> And truly I muſt confeſſe I caſt away this <hi>Stone,</hi> for I <hi>miſplace</hi> it: I contribute that to the <hi>Fabrick,</hi> which the <hi>Builders</hi> in all ages have <hi>refuſed.</hi> But leſt I ſeeme to act <hi>Sine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito,</hi> I muſt tell you I doe it not for this <hi>Generation,</hi> for they are as farre from <hi>Fire,</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> is from <hi>Smoke.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me if you c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, for I have told you an honeſt <hi>Truth.</hi> I write Bookes, as the old <hi>Roman</hi> planted Trees, <hi>Poſteris &amp; Diis immortalibus:</hi> for the <hi>glorie</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>benefit</hi> of <hi>Poſteritie.</hi> It is my <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne</hi> to make over my <hi>Reputation</hi> to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Age,</hi> for in this I would not <hi>injoy</hi> it,
<pb facs="tcp:170666:5"/>becauſe I know not any from whom I would <hi>receive it:</hi> And here you ſee how <hi>ambitious</hi> am growne, but if you judge the <hi>humor amiſs,</hi> tell me not of it, leſt I ſhould <hi>laugh</hi> at you: I look indeed a <hi>ſtep further</hi> then your <hi>lives,</hi> and if you think I may <hi>dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you,</hi> I would have you know, it is the way to goe <hi>beyond you:</hi> To be ſhort, if you attempt this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> you doe it without my adviſe, for it is not fitted to your <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</hi> There is a <hi>white Magic</hi> this book is <hi>inchanted</hi> withal: it is an <hi>adventure</hi> for <hi>Knights</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the <hi>Errants</hi> of this <hi>time</hi> may not <hi>finiſh</hi> it. I ſpeake this to the <hi>Univerſitie Quixots,</hi> and to thoſe only who are <hi>ill-diſpos'd,</hi> as well as <hi>ill-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli'nd;</hi> there is amongſt them a <hi>generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Waſps,</hi> things that will <hi>fight</hi> though never <hi>provok'd:</hi> Theſe <hi>buckle</hi> on their <hi>Logick</hi> as <hi>proof,</hi> but it fares with <hi>them,</hi> as with the famous <hi>Don,</hi> they miſtakea, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> for a <hi>Helmet;</hi> for mine owne part I am no <hi>Reformer,</hi> I can well enough <hi>tolerate</hi> their <hi>poſitions,</hi> ſo they doe not <hi>trouble mine.</hi> What I write is no <hi>rule</hi> for <hi>them,</hi> it is a <hi>Legacie</hi> defer'd to <hi>poſteritie,</hi> for the
<pb facs="tcp:170666:6"/>
               <hi>future times,</hi> wearied with the <hi>vanities</hi> of the <hi>preſent,</hi> will perhaps ſeek after the <hi>Truth,</hi> and gladly entertaine it. Thus you ſee what <hi>Readers</hi> I have <hi>predeſtin'd</hi> for my ſelf, but if any preſent <hi>Maſtix</hi> faſtens on this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> I wiſh him not to <hi>traduce</hi> it, leſt I ſhould <hi>whip</hi> him for it: This is my <hi>adviſe,</hi> which if it be well obſerv'd, 'tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I may <hi>communicate</hi> more of this <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> I may ſtand up like the <hi>Pharus</hi> in a <hi>dark night,</hi> and hold out that <hi>Lamp,</hi> which <hi>Philalethes</hi> hath overcaſt with that <hi>envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous phraſe</hi> of the <hi>Rabbins, Saepes ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſilentium.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170666:6"/>
            <head>Aula Lucis, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have reſolved with my ſelf, to diſcourſe of <hi>Light,</hi> and to deliver it over to the hands of poſteritie, a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice certainly very <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> and <hi>firſt uſed</hi> by thoſe who were <hi>firſt wiſe.</hi> It was us'd then for <hi>Charitie,</hi> not for <hi>pomp,</hi> the <hi>deſigns</hi> of thoſe <hi>Authors,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing in them of <hi>glorie,</hi> but much of <hi>benefit;</hi> it was not their intention to brag, that they themſelvs <hi>did ſee,</hi> but to <hi>lead thoſe,</hi> who in ſome ſenſe were <hi>blind,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170666:7"/>and did <hi>not ſee:</hi> To effect this, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not as ſome <hi>modern Babarians</hi> doe, by clamorous, malicious <hi>diſputes;</hi> a calme <hi>inſtruction</hi> was propos'd, and that being once <hi>rejected,</hi> was never afterwards <hi>urged;</hi> ſo different, and remote a <hi>path</hi> from the the <hi>School-men</hi> did they walk in, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily they might well doe it, for their <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> being once <hi>reſiſted,</hi> they could not inflict a greater <hi>puniſhment</hi> on their <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries,</hi> then to <hi>conceale</hi> them. Had their doctrine been ſuch as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> profeſs now, their <hi>ſilence</hi> indeed had been a <hi>vertue,</hi> but their <hi>poſitions</hi> were not meer <hi>noyſe</hi> and <hi>Notion,</hi> they were moſt deep experimental <hi>ſecrets,</hi> and thoſe of infinite uſe, and <hi>Benefit:</hi> Such a <hi>traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> then as theirs was, may wear that ſtyle of the noble <hi>Verulam,</hi> and is moſt juſtly called <hi>traditio Lampadis.</hi> But I obſerve, that in their <hi>deliverie</hi> of <hi>myſteries,</hi> they have as in all things elſe, imitated <hi>nature,</hi> who diſpenſeth nor her light without her ſhadows: they have provided a <hi>Veile</hi> for their <hi>Art,</hi> not ſo much for <hi>obſcuritie</hi> as <hi>ornament,</hi> and yet I cannot deny but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170666:7"/>ſome of them, have rather buried the <hi>truth</hi> then <hi>dreſt it;</hi> for my own part, I ſhall obſerve a <hi>meane way,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too <hi>obſcure,</hi> nor too <hi>open,</hi> but ſuch as may ſerve <hi>poſteritie,</hi> and add ſome <hi>ſplendor</hi> to the <hi>Science</hi> it ſelfe, And now whoſoever thou art, that in <hi>times</hi> to <hi>come,</hi> ſhalt caſt thine eyes on this <hi>book,</hi> if thou art corrupted with the <hi>common Philoſophie,</hi> doe not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>rage,</hi> and take up the pen in defiance of what is <hi>here written.</hi> It may be thou haſt ſtudied thy three queſtions <hi>pro forma,</hi> and a quick <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant</hi> thou art: but haſt thou <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted</hi> the whole <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Philoſophie?</hi> haſt thou made <hi>nature</hi> the onely <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of thy <hi>life?</hi> and baſt thou arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at laſt to an infallible, <hi>experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal knowledge?</hi> If none of theſe things, upon what foundation doſt thou <hi>build?</hi> It is meer <hi>quacking</hi> to oppoſe the <hi>dead,</hi> and ſuch perhaps as thy betters durſt not <hi>attempt</hi> in time of <hi>life,</hi> but as one ſaid, that <hi>advantage</hi> breeds <hi>baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> ſo ſome may inſult becauſe their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170666:8"/>
               <hi>Adverſarie</hi> is out of the <hi>way,</hi> and tell mee with that friendly <hi>Stoick.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Audiſnê hoc Amphiarae ſub ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram abdite?</q>
            <p>If any ſuch <hi>Tares</hi> ſpring above ground, when I am under it, I have alreadie looked upon them as an idle, contemptible <hi>bundle,</hi> I have prepar'd them a convenient <hi>Deſtinie,</hi> and by my preſent <hi>Scorn,</hi> annihilated their future <hi>malice:</hi> It is a better and more ſerious <hi>Generation</hi> I would bee <hi>ſerviceable</hi> unto, <hi>Generation</hi> that ſeek <hi>nature</hi> in the <hi>ſimplicitie</hi> thereof, and follow her not only with the <hi>Tong,</hi> but with the <hi>hand.</hi> If thou art ſuch then as this <hi>Character</hi> ſpeakes, let me adviſe thee not to <hi>deſpaire;</hi> give me leave alſo to affirm unto thee, and that on my <hi>ſoule,</hi> that the <hi>conſequences</hi> and <hi>treaſures</hi> of this <hi>Art,</hi> are <hi>ſuch,</hi> and ſo <hi>great,</hi> that thy beſt and higheſt <hi>wiſhes</hi> are farre <hi>ſhort</hi> of them, reade then with <hi>diligence</hi> what I ſhall <hi>write,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170666:8"/>to thy <hi>diligence</hi> add <hi>patience,</hi> to thy patience <hi>hope,</hi> for I tell thee neither <hi>fables</hi> nor <hi>follies.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—Tibi res Antiquae laudis, &amp; Artis Aggredior, Sanctos auſus recludere fontes.</q>
            <p>I tell thee a <hi>Truth,</hi> as ancient as the <hi>fundamentals</hi> of the <hi>world:</hi> and now leſt my <hi>Preface</hi> ſhould exceed in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> to the diſcourſe it ſelfe, which muſt bee but <hi>ſhort,</hi> I will quit this kind <hi>out-work,</hi> that I may bring thee within <hi>doores,</hi> and here will I ſhew thee the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> and the <hi>Chryſtalline Court</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Light</hi> originally had no other birth then <hi>manifeſtation,</hi> for it was not made but diſcovered, it is properly the <hi>life</hi> of every <hi>thing,</hi> and it is that which <hi>Acts</hi> in all <hi>particulars,</hi> but the <hi>communion</hi> thereof with the <hi>firſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was celebrated by a <hi>generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> before any <hi>particulars</hi> were <hi>made;</hi> the matter of it ſelf was a <hi>paſſive thin
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170666:9"/>Subſtance,</hi> but <hi>apt</hi> to retaine <hi>Light,</hi> as <hi>Smoke,</hi> is to retaine <hi>flame.</hi> After <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnation,</hi> it was condens'd to a <hi>Chryſtalline moiſture, unctuons</hi> and <hi>fiery,</hi> of <hi>nature Hermaphroditical,</hi> and this in a <hi>double ſenſe,</hi> in relation to a <hi>double Center, Celeſtial,</hi> and <hi>Terreſtrial.</hi> From the <hi>Terreſtrial Center</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>earthly Venus,</hi> which is <hi>Fierie</hi> and <hi>Maſculine,</hi> and the <hi>earthly Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> which is <hi>Waterie</hi> and <hi>Faeminine;</hi> and theſe <hi>two</hi> are <hi>one againſt</hi> the <hi>other.</hi> From the <hi>Celeſtiall Center</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded two living <hi>Images,</hi> namely a <hi>White,</hi> and a <hi>Red light,</hi> and the <hi>white light</hi> ſetled in the <hi>Water,</hi> but the <hi>Red</hi> went into the <hi>Earth.</hi> Hence you may gather ſome infallible <hi>ſignes,</hi> whereby you may direct your ſelves in the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Matter,</hi> and in the <hi>Operation</hi> it ſelfe, when the <hi>Matter</hi> is <hi>knowne.</hi> For if you have the true <hi>Sperm,</hi> and know withall how to <hi>prepare</hi> it, which cannot bee without our <hi>ſecret fire;</hi> you ſhall find that the <hi>Matter</hi> no ſoonerſeels the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170666:9"/>heat,</hi> but the <hi>white light</hi> will lift himſelf above the <hi>water,</hi> and there will hee <hi>ſwim</hi> in his glorious <hi>blew ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiment</hi> like the <hi>Heavens.</hi> But that I may ſpeak ſomthing more concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Chaos</hi> it ſelf, I muſt tell you it is not <hi>rain-water,</hi> nor <hi>dew;</hi> but it is a <hi>ſubtile mineral moiſture,</hi> a <hi>water</hi> ſo extreamly <hi>thin</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> with ſuch a tranſcendent incredible <hi>bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> there is not in all <hi>nature</hi> any <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor</hi> like it, but <hi>it ſelf.</hi> In plain terms it is the <hi>middle ſubſtance</hi> of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's <hi>Mercurie,</hi> a water that is <hi>coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable,</hi> and may bee <hi>bardned</hi> by a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per heat</hi> into <hi>ſtones,</hi> and <hi>metals:</hi> Hence it was, that the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> cald it their <hi>ſtone,</hi> or if it be lawful for mee to reveal that, which the <hi>Devil</hi> out of <hi>envie,</hi> would not diſcover to <hi>Illardus,</hi> I ſay they cal'd it a <hi>ſtone,</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> that no man might know what it was they cal'd ſo: for, there is nothing in the world ſo <hi>remote</hi> from the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion</hi> of a <hi>ſtone,</hi> for it is <hi>water,</hi> and no <hi>ſtone.</hi> Now what <hi>water</hi> it is, I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170666:10"/>have told you already, and for your better inſtruction I ſhal tell you more: it is a water made by nature, not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted</hi> by the hands of <hi>Man,</hi> nor is it <hi>meere water,</hi> but a <hi>ſpermatic viſcous compoſition</hi> of <hi>Water, Earth, Air,</hi> and <hi>Fire;</hi> all theſe foure nature unites in one <hi>Chryſtalline coagulable Maſs,</hi> in the form or appearance of <hi>water,</hi> and therefore I told you it was <hi>a water</hi> made by <hi>nature:</hi> But if you ask mee how <hi>nature</hi> may be ſaid to <hi>make</hi> any ſuch <hi>water,</hi> I ſhall inſtruct you by an example that's obvious. <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>water</hi> are the onely <hi>materials</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>nature</hi> works, for theſe <hi>two</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>paſſive,</hi> are compaſſed about with the <hi>active ſuperior bodies,</hi> namely, with the <hi>Aire, Heaven, Sun</hi> and <hi>Stars.</hi> Thus doe they ſtand in the <hi>very fire,</hi> at leaſt under the <hi>Beams</hi> and <hi>ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> thereof, ſo that the <hi>Earth</hi> is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to a continual <hi>torrefaction,</hi> and the water to a continuall <hi>coction:</hi> Hence it comes to paſs, that wee are perpetually overcaſt with <hi>Clouds,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170666:10"/>this by a Phyſicall <hi>Extraction</hi> or <hi>ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of <hi>water,</hi> which <hi>nature</hi> herſelf <hi>diſtils,</hi> and <hi>rains</hi> downe upon the <hi>earth:</hi> Now, this <hi>water,</hi> though of a different complexion, from the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher's <hi>Mineral water,</hi> yet hath it many <hi>circumſtances,</hi> that well deſerve our <hi>obſervation.</hi> I ſhall not inſiſt long upon any, I will onely give you one or two <hi>inſtances,</hi> and then <hi>returne</hi> to my <hi>ſubject.</hi> Firſt of all then, you are to conſider, that <hi>nature</hi> diſtils not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>body,</hi> as the <hi>Chymiſt</hi> doth in the <hi>Recipient;</hi> ſhe drawes the water up from the <hi>Earth,</hi> and to the <hi>ſame earth</hi> doth ſhe returne it, and hence it is, that ſhee generates by <hi>circular</hi> and ſeaſonable <hi>imbibitions.</hi> Secondly, you muſt obſerve, that ſhee <hi>prepares</hi> her <hi>moiſture</hi> before ſhee <hi>imbibes</hi> the <hi>body</hi> therewith, and that by a moſt <hi>admirable preparation;</hi> her <hi>nethod</hi> in this point is very obvious and <hi>open</hi> to all the <hi>World,</hi> ſo that if <hi>men</hi> were not <hi>blind,</hi> I needed not much to <hi>ſpeak</hi> of it. Her <hi>water</hi> (wee ſee) ſhee <hi>rariſies</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170666:11"/>into <hi>Clouds,</hi> and by this <hi>meanes</hi> doth ſhee <hi>rack</hi> and <hi>tenter-ſtretch</hi> the <hi>body,</hi> ſo that all the <hi>parts</hi> thereof are <hi>expos'd</hi> to a ſearching ſpiritual <hi>purgatorie</hi> of <hi>winde</hi> and <hi>fire;</hi> for, her <hi>wind</hi> paſſeth quite through the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and when they are <hi>well cleanſed,</hi> then comes <hi>Heaven</hi> in with her <hi>Fire,</hi> and <hi>fixeth</hi> it in <hi>Ente puro Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirico:</hi> But this is not <hi>all,</hi> there are other <hi>circumstances,</hi> which <hi>nature</hi> uſeth <hi>above ground,</hi> in order to her <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables,</hi> and now would I ſpeak of her <hi>ſubterraneous preparations,</hi> in order to her <hi>Minerals,</hi> but that is not <hi>lawfull</hi> for <hi>mee</hi> as it was for the <hi>Poet,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Pandere res altâ terrâ, &amp; Caligine merſas.</q>
            <p>Howſover I ſhall not fail to tell thee a conſiderable <hi>truth,</hi> whoever thou art that ſtudieſt this <hi>difficult Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> The <hi>preparation</hi> of our <hi>Animal</hi> and <hi>Mineral ſperm</hi> (I ſpeak of the <hi>true preparation</hi>) is a <hi>ſecret</hi> upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170666:11"/>which <hi>God</hi> hath laid his <hi>Seale,</hi> and thou mayſt not <hi>find</hi> it in <hi>books,</hi> for it was never intirely <hi>written,</hi> thy beſt courſe is to conſider the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> for there it may bee <hi>found,</hi> but not without reiterated, deep, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>meditations.</hi> If this <hi>Attempt</hi> fails thee, thou muſt <hi>pray</hi> for it (not that I hold it an <hi>eaſie</hi> or a common thing to attaine to <hi>Revelations,</hi> for wee have <hi>none</hi> in <hi>England</hi>) but <hi>God</hi> may <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover</hi> it to <hi>thee,</hi> by ſome <hi>ordinarie</hi> and meere <hi>natural meanes:</hi> In a word, if thou canſt not attaine to the <hi>knowledg</hi> of it in this <hi>life,</hi> yet ſhalt thou know it in thy <hi>own body,</hi> when thou art paſt knowing of it in this <hi>Subject;</hi> but becauſ I will not deprive thee of thoſe <hi>helps</hi> which I may <hi>lawfully</hi> communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, I tell thee that our <hi>preparation</hi> is a <hi>purgation,</hi> yet doe not wee <hi>purge</hi> by common ridi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uous <hi>ſublimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> nor the more fooliſh <hi>filtrations,</hi> by a ſecret, tangible, <hi>natural fire,</hi> and hee that knowes this <hi>Fire,</hi> and how to waſh with it, knowes the <hi>key</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170666:12"/>of our <hi>Art,</hi> even our hidden <hi>Saturn,</hi> and the ſtupendious <hi>infernall lavato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> of <hi>nature;</hi> much more could I ſay concerning this <hi>Fire,</hi> and the <hi>proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> thereof, it being one of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>myſteries</hi> of the <hi>Creation,</hi> a ſubject queſtionleſs wherein I might bee <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous,</hi> and all the way <hi>myſterious,</hi> for it relates the greateſt <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Magic,</hi> being the <hi>firſt male</hi> of the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie,</hi> and <hi>almoſt</hi> his <hi>Mother:</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then the <hi>Generation</hi> of our <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and how he is made, for here lyes the <hi>ground</hi> of all our <hi>ſecrets.</hi> It is plain that <hi>outwardly</hi> wee ſee nothing but what is <hi>groſſe,</hi> for example, <hi>Earth, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Metals, Stones,</hi> and amongſt the better Creatures <hi>Man</hi> himſelfe. All theſe <hi>things</hi> have a lumpiſh, ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual <hi>outſide,</hi> but <hi>inwardly</hi> they are <hi>full</hi> of a ſubtil, vital <hi>limoſitie</hi> impregnated with <hi>fire,</hi> and this <hi>nature</hi> makes <hi>uſe</hi> of in <hi>generations,</hi> wherefore wee call it the <hi>ſperm:</hi> For inſtance ſake, wee know the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> is not his <hi>ſperm,</hi> but the <hi>ſperm</hi> is a ſubtil <hi>extraction</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170666:12"/>out of his <hi>bodie:</hi> Even ſo in the <hi>great world,</hi> the bodie or <hi>fabric</hi> it ſelf, is not the <hi>ſeed,</hi> it is not <hi>Earth, Water, Aire,</hi> or <hi>Fire:</hi> for theſe <hi>foure</hi> if they were put <hi>together,</hi> would bee ſtill <hi>four Bodies</hi> of <hi>different formes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions.</hi> The <hi>ſeed</hi> then, or <hi>firſt matter</hi> is a certaine <hi>limoſitie</hi> extracted from theſe <hi>foure,</hi> for every one of them contributes from its very <hi>Center,</hi> a thin <hi>ſlimie ſubſtance,</hi> and of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>ſlimes</hi> nature makes the <hi>ſperme</hi> by an ineſſable <hi>union</hi> and <hi>mixture;</hi> this <hi>mixture</hi> and <hi>compoſition</hi> of <hi>ſlimie principles,</hi> is that <hi>Maſs</hi> which wee call the <hi>firſt matter,</hi> it is the <hi>Minera</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> whereof God made him; in a <hi>double image</hi> did hee <hi>make</hi> him in the <hi>day</hi> that he becam a <hi>living ſoule;</hi> hence a famous <hi>Artiſi</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> and alluding to the <hi>firſt matter,</hi> delivers himſelf in theſe terms. <hi>Creavit Deus Adam de limoſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Elementorum, ſcilicet de limo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate Terrae, Aquae, Aeris, &amp;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170666:13"/>Ignis, &amp; vivificavit eum a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Sancti Spiritus, &amp; de Luce, &amp; claritate, &amp; lumine Mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Have a care then that you miſtake not any <hi>ſpecified body</hi> for the <hi>ſperm,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of <hi>quick-ſilver, Antinomie,</hi> and all the <hi>metals,</hi> and have nothing to doe with <hi>ought</hi> that is <hi>extracted</hi> from <hi>metals.</hi> Beware of <hi>Salts, Vitriols,</hi> and everie <hi>minor mineral:</hi> beware of <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals,</hi> and <hi>Vegetables,</hi> and of every <hi>thing</hi> that is particular, or takes <hi>place</hi> in the <hi>Claſſis</hi> of any knowne <hi>ſpecies.</hi> The <hi>firſt matter</hi> is a miraculous <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> and of which you may affirme <hi>contraries</hi> without <hi>Inconvenience.</hi> It is very <hi>weake,</hi> and yet moſt <hi>ſtrong,</hi> it is exceſſively ſoft, and yet there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo <hi>hard.</hi> It is <hi>one</hi> and <hi>all: ſpirit</hi> and <hi>body: fixt</hi> and <hi>volatile, Male</hi> and <hi>Female: viſible</hi> and <hi>inviflble.</hi> It is <hi>fire,</hi> and <hi>burnes not:</hi> it is <hi>water,</hi> and <hi>wets not,</hi> it is <hi>Earth</hi> that <hi>runs,</hi> and <hi>Aire</hi> that <hi>ſtands ſtill;</hi> in a word it is <hi>Mercurie,</hi> the <hi>laughter</hi> of <hi>fools,</hi> and the <hi>wonder</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170666:13"/>of the <hi>wiſe,</hi> nor hath <hi>God</hi> made any <hi>thing</hi> that is <hi>like</hi> him. Hee is <hi>borne</hi> in the <hi>VVorld,</hi> but was extant <hi>before</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> and hence that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Riddle,</hi> which hee hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where propos'd of himſelfe. <hi>Habito in Montibus &amp; in Plani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, pater antequam Filius: ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui matrem meam, &amp; mater mea, ſive pater tulit me in matrice ſua generans me, non opus habens Nutrice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dwell (ſaith hee) in the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> and in the <hi>Plains,</hi> a <hi>Father</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was a <hi>Son:</hi> I <hi>generated</hi> my <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and my <hi>mother</hi> carrying mee in her <hi>womb</hi> generated <hi>mee,</hi> having no <hi>uye</hi> for a <hi>Nurſe.</hi> This is that <hi>ſubſtance</hi> which at <hi>preſent</hi> is the <hi>Child</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon;</hi> but <hi>originally</hi> both his <hi>Parents</hi> came <hi>out</hi> of his <hi>Belly.</hi> Hee is plac'd between <hi>two fires,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ever <hi>reſtleſs.</hi> Hee growes out of the <hi>earth</hi> as all <hi>vegetables</hi> doe, and in the darkeſt night that is, receives a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170666:14"/>
               <hi>light</hi> from the <hi>ſtarrs,</hi> and reteins it. Hee is <hi>attractive</hi> at the firſt, becauſe of his <hi>horrible emptines,</hi> and what hee <hi>drawes</hi> downe is a <hi>Priſoner</hi> for <hi>ever;</hi> hee hath in him a <hi>thick fire,</hi> by which hee <hi>captivates</hi> the <hi>Thin,</hi> and he is both <hi>Artiſt</hi> and <hi>matter</hi> to himſelfe. In his <hi>firſt appearance</hi> he is neither <hi>earth</hi> nor <hi>water,</hi> neither <hi>ſolid</hi> nor <hi>fluid,</hi> but a <hi>ſubſtance</hi> without <hi>all forme,</hi> but what is <hi>univerſal;</hi> hee is <hi>viſible,</hi> but of no certaine colour, for <hi>Chamaelion-like,</hi> hee puts on all colours, and there is nothing in the world hath the ſame <hi>figure</hi> with <hi>him;</hi> when hee is purg'd from his <hi>Accidents,</hi> hee is a <hi>water</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourd with <hi>fire, deep</hi> to the <hi>ſight,</hi> and as it were <hi>ſwollen,</hi> and he hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him that <hi>reſembles</hi> a commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a <hi>vaporous heate</hi> hee opens his <hi>belly,</hi> and diſcovers an <hi>azure Heaven,</hi> ting'd with a <hi>milkie light,</hi> within this <hi>coelum</hi> hee hides a little <hi>Sun,</hi> a moſt powerfull <hi>red fire,</hi> ſparkling like a <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncle,</hi> which is the <hi>red gold</hi> of the <hi>wiſe-men.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170666:14"/>our <hi>ſealed fountain,</hi> and though many deſire them, yet none <hi>enters</hi> here, but hee that knowes the <hi>Key,</hi> and withall <hi>how</hi> to <hi>uſe</hi> it; in the <hi>bottom</hi> of this <hi>Well</hi> lyes an old <hi>Dragon,</hi> ſtretch't a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and faſt <hi>aſleep;</hi> awake her if you can, and make her <hi>drinke,</hi> for by this meanes ſhee will recover her <hi>youth,</hi> and bee <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to you for ever, in a word, ſeparate the <hi>Eagle</hi> from the <hi>Green-Lyon,</hi> then clip her <hi>wings,</hi> and you have perform'd a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle:</hi> but theſe you'l ſay are <hi>blind termes,</hi> and no man knowes what to make of them. True indeed, but they are <hi>ſuch</hi> as we received from the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers;</hi> howſoever that I may deal plainly with you. the <hi>Eagle</hi> is the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for it is <hi>volatil,</hi> and flies up in <hi>Clouds</hi> as an <hi>Eagle</hi> doth, but I ſpeak not of any <hi>common water</hi> whatſoever. The <hi>greene Lion</hi> is the <hi>Body</hi> or <hi>Magicall earth,</hi> with which you muſt clip the <hi>wings</hi> of the <hi>Eagle,</hi> that is to ſay, you muſt fix her, that ſhee may fly no more. By this wee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170666:15"/>underſtand the <hi>opening,</hi> and <hi>ſhutting</hi> of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> &amp; that cannot be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the proper <hi>key,</hi> I meane our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>fire,</hi> wherein conſiſts the whole <hi>myſterie</hi> of the <hi>preparation;</hi> our <hi>fire</hi> then is a <hi>naturall fire,</hi> it is <hi>vaporous, ſubtil,</hi> and <hi>piercing;</hi> it is that which <hi>workes</hi> all in all, if wee looke on <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical digeſtions,</hi> nor is there any thing in the <hi>world</hi> that anſwers to the <hi>ſtomack,</hi> and performes the <hi>effects</hi> thereof, but this <hi>one thing,</hi> it is a <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of proprietie <hi>ſolar,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſulphureous;</hi> it is prepar'd as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> tell us, <hi>ab antiquo Draco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> and in plaine termes, it is the <hi>fume</hi> of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> not <hi>erude</hi> but <hi>cocted.</hi> This <hi>Fume</hi> utterly deſtroyes the <hi>firſt forme</hi> of <hi>gold,</hi> introducing a <hi>ſecond,</hi> and a more noble one. By <hi>Mercurie</hi> I underſtand not <hi>quick ſilver,</hi> but <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Philoſophicall,</hi> which devoures the <hi>Moone,</hi> and keeps her alwaies in his <hi>Belly:</hi> by <hi>gold,</hi> I meane our <hi>ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matic green gold,</hi> not the ador'd Lump which is dead, and ineffectuall, it were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170666:15"/>well certainly for the <hi>Students</hi> of this <hi>noble Art,</hi> if they reſolved on ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>poſitions,</hi> before they attempted the <hi>books</hi> of the <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Example, let them take along with them theſe few <hi>Truths,</hi> and they will ſerve them for ſo many <hi>rules,</hi> whereby they may <hi>cenſure,</hi> and <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> their Authors.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the <hi>firſt matter</hi> of the <hi>ſtone,</hi> is the very <hi>ſame</hi> with the <hi>firſt matter</hi> of all <hi>things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That in this <hi>matter</hi> all the <hi>eſſential principles,</hi> or <hi>ingredients</hi> of the <hi>Elixir,</hi> are already <hi>ſhut</hi> up by <hi>Nature,</hi> and that wee muſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to add any thing to this <hi>matter,</hi> but what wee have <hi>formerly drawne</hi> out of it; for the <hi>ſtone</hi> excludes all <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions,</hi> but what <hi>diſtill imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly</hi> from its owne <hi>Chryſtalline uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Minera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, that the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers have their peculiar <hi>ſecret me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> quite <hi>different</hi> from the <hi>metals</hi> of the <hi>vulgar,</hi> for where they name <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170666:16"/>they mind not <hi>Quick-ſilver;</hi> where <hi>Saturn</hi> not <hi>lead,</hi> where <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> not <hi>Coper</hi> and <hi>Iron,</hi> and where <hi>Sol</hi> or <hi>Luna,</hi> not <hi>gold</hi> or <hi>ſilver.</hi> Their <hi>ſtone</hi> verily is not made of <hi>common gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver,</hi> but it is <hi>made</hi> as one delivers it, <hi>Ex Auro &amp; Argento vilibus, faetentibus ſimul &amp; ſuaveolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, virentibus, animatis, ubique repertitiis, ſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum quam paucis cognitis,</hi> Of <hi>gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver</hi> that are reputed <hi>baſe</hi> that <hi>ſtinke,</hi> and withall <hi>ſmel ſweetly,</hi> of <hi>green, living gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver</hi> to bee found <hi>every where,</hi> but known of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few: away then with thoſe <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks,</hi> who tell you of <hi>Antinomie, ſalts, Vitriols, Marchaſits,</hi> or any <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> whatſoever; Away alſo with ſuch Authors as preſcribe or practiſe upon any of theſe <hi>bodies,</hi> you may be ſure they were meer <hi>cheats,</hi> and did write onely to gaine an <hi>opinion</hi> of <hi>knowledge:</hi> There are indeed ſome uncharitable but knowing <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170666:16"/>who ſtick not to <hi>lead</hi> the <hi>blind</hi> out of this way; theſe are full of elaborate ſtudied <hi>deceits,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> of them who pretends to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> hath at the ſame <hi>mouth</hi> vented a <hi>ſlipperie</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, namely, that the <hi>ſtone</hi> cannot bee <hi>opened</hi> thorough all the <hi>grounds</hi> as hee cals them, under <hi>ſeven years.</hi> Truely, I am of opinion that hee never knew the ſtone in this <hi>naturall world,</hi> but how well acquainted hee was with the <hi>Tinctures</hi> in the <hi>ſpiritual world,</hi> I will not <hi>determine.</hi> I muſt confeſs many <hi>brave,</hi> and <hi>ſublime truths,</hi> have fallen from his <hi>Pen,</hi> but when he deſcends from his <hi>inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and ſtoopes to a <hi>Phyſical practiſe,</hi> hee is quite <hi>beſides</hi> the <hi>But.</hi> I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver admir'd the royal <hi>Gieberim,</hi> whoſe <hi>religion</hi> if you queſtion, I can produce it in theſe few words, <hi>Sublimis natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum Deus, Benedictus, &amp; glorioſus.</hi> This is the <hi>title,</hi> and the <hi>ſtyle</hi> hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beſtowes upon <hi>God,</hi> and it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>prove</hi> him no Atheiſt. Hee I ſay, hath ſo <hi>freely,</hi> and in truth ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170666:17"/>
               <hi>plainly</hi> diſcovered this <hi>ſecret,</hi> that had hee not <hi>mixt</hi> his many impertinencies with it, he had directly <hi>proſtituted</hi> the <hi>myſterie.</hi> what I ſpeak, is apparent to all <hi>knowing</hi> Artiſts, and hence it is that moſt <hi>Maſters</hi> have ſo honour'd this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabian,</hi> that in their books hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly cal'd <hi>Magiſter magiſtrorum;</hi> we are indeed more beholding to this <hi>Prince,</hi> who did not know <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then to many profeſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> for they have not onely <hi>conceal'd</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> but they have publiſh'd <hi>falſities,</hi> and meere <hi>inconſiſtencies</hi> therewith, they have <hi>ſtudiouſly,</hi> and of meer purpoſe <hi>deceiv'd</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> without any reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of their <hi>credit</hi> or <hi>Conſcience.</hi> It is a great <hi>Queſtion,</hi> who was moſt <hi>envious</hi> the
<note n="a" place="margin">This receip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was extant in Bodiley' Archieves.</note> 
               <hi>Devil</hi> in his <hi>Recipe</hi> to our <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-Docter,</hi> or
<note n="b" place="margin">See Arnol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us his Flos Florum.</note> 
               <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldus</hi> in his <hi>accipe</hi> to the King of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> I know well enough what that Gentleman <hi>de Villa novâ</hi> preſcribes, and I know withall his inſtructions
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170666:17"/>are ſo difficult that <hi>Count Trevers</hi> when he was Adept <hi>ſuo modo,</hi> could not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi> them: for hee hath written moſt egregious <hi>Non-ſenſe,</hi> and this by endeavouring to confute greater <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> then hee did <hi>apprehend.</hi> Now if any man thinkes mee too <hi>bold,</hi> for cenſuring ſo great an <hi>Artiſt</hi> as <hi>Arnoldus</hi> was, I am not ſo <hi>emptie,</hi> but I can <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> for my ſelf; I charge him not with want of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> but want of <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> a <hi>point</hi> wherein even the <hi>poſſeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Philoſopher's ſtone</hi> are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>poore.</hi> I ſpeak this, becauſe I pitty the <hi>diſtractions</hi> of our moderne <hi>Alchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> though <hi>Thilalethes</hi> laughs in his <hi>ſleeve,</hi> and like a young Colt kicks at that <hi>Name.</hi> For my own part I adviſe no <hi>Man</hi> to attempt this Art without a <hi>Maſter,</hi> for though you know the <hi>Matter,</hi> yet are you farr <hi>ſhort</hi> of the <hi>Medicine.</hi> This is a <hi>Truth</hi> you may be confident of, and if you will not believe my Text, take it upon <hi>Raymund Lullie's</hi> Experience, Hee knew the <hi>Matter,</hi> it being the firſt thing his <hi>Maſter</hi> taught
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170666:18"/>him, then hee practic'd upon it in his own phraſe, <hi>multifariè multis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> modis:</hi> but all was to no <hi>purpoſe,</hi> hee had the <hi>Cabinet</hi> but not the <hi>Key.</hi> At laſt hee found himſelf to bee (what many <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> are) a confident <hi>Quack,</hi> a <hi>Broy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and nothing more, as it appears by his <hi>ſubſequent</hi> confeſſion. <hi>Eleganter</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>dixerunt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phi, quod opus magnum non eſt niſi ſolutio &amp; Congelatio, ſed iſta fiunt per viam Circulorum, quorum ignorantiâ plures Magnates in lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratura decepti fuerunt in magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, credentes notabiliter cum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidentiâ, ſe intelligere formam, &amp; modum Circulandi, ex quibus nos fuiſſe unum lethaliter vulner atum celare non intendimus. Cum ſola enim preſumptione &amp; temeritate, ſcientiae hujus naturam firmiter nos intelligere credebamus, ſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170666:18"/>nullo modo intelleximus, donec tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus adfuit, in quo ſpiritus nos docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, non immediatè ſed mediate per Magiſtrum Arnoldum de Villa nova qui largitate ſuà immenſà refici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter in nos inſpiravit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he: and now I ſhall adviſe the <hi>Chymiſt</hi> to ſet a watch at his <hi>lips,</hi> becauſe of ſome inviſible <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verheare.</hi> I my ſelfe have known <hi>ſome men</hi> to <hi>affirme,</hi> they had <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>done</hi> ſuch <hi>things,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>doe</hi> according to the <hi>preſent Laws</hi> of <hi>Creation,</hi> but had my young friend <hi>Eugenius Philalethes</hi> been preſent, hee had <hi>langh'd</hi> without mercie. Take heed then what you ſay, leaſt you make <hi>ſport</hi> for the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> for they are ſomething like the <hi>immortals.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>Many men there are, who think it <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie</hi> to be inſtructed in theſe ſecrets,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170666:19"/>but in this they are confidently miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Hee muſt bee a knowne tryed <hi>Friend,</hi> a friend of <hi>years,</hi> not of <hi>dayes;</hi> not a <hi>complement all thing,</hi> whoſe <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is all <hi>Hypocrit:</hi> not a <hi>ſevere diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler</hi> who gives thee <hi>fair words,</hi> but if once <hi>tryed,</hi> his <hi>heart</hi> is ſo ſarr from his <hi>Promiſes,</hi> that like a <hi>Fly</hi> in a <hi>Box,</hi> it is ſcarce a part of his <hi>Body. Raymund Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> hath in a certain place deliver'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf handſomly in relation to the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,</hi> and this for his <hi>friends</hi> ſake; but how <hi>rigid</hi> then was hee <hi>in ſcriptis?</hi> His <hi>Diſciple</hi> (if hee could <hi>underſtand</hi> him) was to bee <hi>accomptable</hi> to him in the <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>myſterie,</hi> and therefore he tels him plainly, that hee did it <hi>mutuo tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; ſub reſtitutione coram judice ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali,</hi> wee muſt not expect then to be <hi>inſtructed,</hi> becauſe wee are <hi>acquainted,</hi> and verily <hi>acquaintance</hi> with ſuch <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> is a <hi>thing</hi> not <hi>common.</hi> In <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie favours</hi> it is ſuppos'd, that men ſhould <hi>deſerve</hi> them, before they <hi>receive</hi> them: but in this <hi>thing,</hi> which is a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit incomparable,</hi> it ſals out <hi>otherwiſe,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170666:19"/>wee looke for preſent <hi>diſcoveries,</hi> wee believe the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> will teach us, and in <hi>plaine</hi> termes tell us all their Art, but wee <hi>know</hi> not <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> they ſhould bee ſo <hi>kind</hi> unto <hi>us.</hi> Such impudent <hi>Hopes</hi> have no more <hi>reaſon</hi> in them, then if I ſhould ſpend a <hi>complement</hi> on a <hi>rich Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and then <hi>expect</hi> hee ſhould make mee his <hi>Heire</hi> in <hi>lieu</hi> of my <hi>phraſe,</hi> and ſo paſſe his <hi>Eſtate</hi> upon mee. This is very abſurd, but nothing more <hi>common,</hi> though I know there is another <hi>ſort</hi> of <hi>well-wiſhers,</hi> but they are <hi>moſt miſerable,</hi> for they caſt about to foole thoſe <hi>men,</hi> whom they know to bee <hi>wiſer</hi> then <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> But in this <hi>point</hi> the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> need no <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> they can act <hi>many parts,</hi> and hee that <hi>plots</hi> to <hi>over-reach</hi> them, takes a <hi>courſe</hi> to <hi>breake</hi> before hee <hi>ſets up.</hi> It remains then, that we beſtow our Attempts on their <hi>Books,</hi> and here wee muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the two <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Natures, Light</hi> and <hi>Matter. Matter</hi> as <hi>I</hi> have formerly intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170666:20"/>is the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> here hee <hi>dwels</hi> and <hi>builds</hi> for himſelf, and to ſpeake Truth, hee takes up his <hi>lodging</hi> in <hi>ſight</hi> of all the <hi>World.</hi> When he firſt <hi>enters</hi> it, it is a glorious <hi>tranſparent Roome,</hi> a <hi>Chryſtall-Caſtle,</hi> and hee lives like a <hi>Familiar</hi> in <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</hi> Hee hath then the <hi>Libertie</hi> to look out at the <hi>Windows,</hi> his <hi>love</hi> is all in his <hi>ſight,</hi> I meane that <hi>liquid Venus,</hi> which <hi>lures</hi> him in, but this continues not very long. Hee is <hi>buſie</hi> as all <hi>Lovers</hi> are, labours for a more cloſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> inſinuates and conveyes <hi>himſelf</hi> into the very <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of his <hi>Love,</hi> ſo that his <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>action</hi> ſtirre up her <hi>moyſt Eſſences,</hi> by whoſe <hi>meanes</hi> he becomes an <hi>abſolute Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> For at laſt the <hi>Earth</hi> growes <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him</hi> out of the <hi>water,</hi> ſo that he is quite ſhut up in <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and this is the <hi>ſecret</hi> of the AEternall God which he hath been pleas'd to reveale to ſome of his <hi>Seruants,</hi> though mortall <hi>Man</hi> was never <hi>worthy</hi> of it. <hi>I</hi> wiſh it were <hi>lawfull</hi> for mee to enlarge my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170666:20"/>ſelfe in this <hi>point</hi> for <hi>Religion's</hi> ſake, but it is not <hi>ſafe,</hi> nor <hi>convenient</hi> that all <hi>Eares</hi> ſhould heare even the <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi> This leprous <hi>Earth</hi> (for ſuch it is if it bee not <hi>pur'gd</hi>) is the <hi>Toad</hi> that eates up the <hi>Eagle,</hi> or <hi>Spirit,</hi> of which there is frequent <hi>mention</hi> in the Philoſopher's <hi>Bookes.</hi> In this <hi>Earth</hi> alſo have many of the <hi>wiſemen</hi> ſeated that <hi>tincture,</hi> which wee commonly call <hi>darkneſſe:</hi> Truly they may as well beſtow it on the <hi>water,</hi> or the <hi>Aire,</hi> for it appears not in any <hi>one element,</hi> but either in all <hi>Foure,</hi> or elſe in <hi>two,</hi> and this <hi>laſt</hi> was that which <hi>deceiv</hi>'d them. Now the <hi>water</hi> hath no <hi>blackneſſe</hi> at all, but a majeſtic, large <hi>Claritie.</hi> The <hi>Earth</hi> likewiſe in her owne <hi>nature</hi> is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Chryſtallized body,</hi> bright as the <hi>Heavens.</hi> The <hi>Aire alſo</hi> excels both theſe in <hi>complexion,</hi> for hee hath in him amoſt ſtrange inexpreſſible <hi>white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>ſerenitie.</hi> As for the <hi>Fire,</hi> it is outwardly <hi>red</hi> and ſhining like a <hi>Jacinth,</hi> but <hi>inwardly</hi> in the ſpirit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170666:21"/>
               <hi>white</hi> as <hi>Milke.</hi> Now if wee put all theſe <hi>ſubſtances</hi> together though <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> and <hi>celified;</hi> yet when they <hi>ſtirre</hi> and worke for <hi>Generation,</hi> the <hi>blacke colour</hi> over-ſpreads them <hi>all,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>blacke,</hi> ſo <hi>deepe</hi> and <hi>horrid,</hi> that no common <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> can be <hi>compared</hi> unto it. I deſire to know then whence this <hi>Tincture</hi> ariſeth, for the <hi>Roote</hi> of every other <hi>Colour</hi> is <hi>known.</hi> It is to be obſerved, that in the <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the <hi>Elements,</hi> this <hi>blackeneſſe</hi> appeares not any where, but in that <hi>Element</hi> which is <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Fire;</hi> and this onely <hi>whiles</hi> you are <hi>drawing</hi> out the <hi>Fire,</hi> for the <hi>Fire</hi> being, <hi>ſeparated</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> is <hi>white.</hi> It is plaine then that <hi>Darkeneſſe</hi> belongs to the <hi>Fire,</hi> for in truth <hi>Fire</hi> is the <hi>Manal</hi> of it, and this is <hi>one</hi> of the greateſt <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> both in <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Philoſophie;</hi> but <hi>thoſe</hi> that would <hi>rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> it, ſhould firſt learne the <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> betweene <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> in his <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> did firſt ſee a pleaſing, glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170666:21"/>
               <hi>Light,</hi> but <hi>interminated.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards appeared a horrible ſad <hi>Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and this moved <hi>downe-wards,</hi> deſcending from the <hi>Eye</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> as if a <hi>Cloud</hi> ſhould come <hi>from</hi> the <hi>Sunne.</hi> This <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> (ſaith he) was condens'd into a <hi>certaine water,</hi> but not without a mournfull inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſſible <hi>Voyce</hi> or <hi>Sound,</hi> as the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours</hi> of the <hi>Elements</hi> are reſolved by <hi>Thunder.</hi> After this (ſaith that great <hi>Philoſopher</hi>) the <hi>holy word</hi> came <hi>out</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> and did <hi>get upon</hi> the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and out of the <hi>water</hi> he made <hi>all Things.</hi> Let it bee your ſtudy then who would know <hi>all things,</hi> to ſeek out this <hi>Secret water,</hi> which hath in it ſelfe <hi>all Things.</hi> This is the <hi>Phiſicall</hi> and famous <hi>Pythagorean Cube,</hi> which ſurpriſeth all <hi>Formes,</hi> and retaines them Priſoners <hi>Huic ſundo</hi> (ſaid my <hi>Capnion</hi>) <hi>Si qua forma demerſa, huic ſolido Receptaculo ſi fuerit illapſa, &amp; in hanc ſedem mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialem repoſita, non vage nec
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170666:22"/>communiter recipitur, ſed ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter &amp; ſingulariter, fit indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua &amp; incommunicabilis, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam aſcriptitia glebae, tempori &amp; loco ſubjecta, &amp; quaſi de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertate in ſervitutem Materiae proſcripta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Conſequences</hi> of this <hi>Priſon,</hi> which ſometimes are <hi>ſad,</hi> and the <hi>ſteps</hi> that <hi>lead</hi> unto it, are moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly expreſt in the <hi>Oracles.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Praecipitium in Terra ſubeſt,</l>
               <l>Septemvios trahens per gradus: ſub quo</l>
               <l>Horribilis Neceſſitatis Thronus eſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In a word all things in the World, as well <hi>Events</hi> as <hi>Subſtances</hi> flow out of this <hi>VVell.</hi> Hence come our <hi>fortunes</hi> and our <hi>misfortunes,</hi> our <hi>Riches</hi> and our <hi>povertie:</hi> and this according to the <hi>ſcales</hi> of the <hi>ſupreme Agent</hi> in his <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> wee ſee there is a certain <hi>face</hi> of <hi>light</hi> in all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170666:22"/>thoſe <hi>things</hi> which are very <hi>deare,</hi> or very <hi>precious</hi> to us. For Example, in <hi>Beautie, Gold, Silver, Pearls,</hi> and in every <hi>thing</hi> that is <hi>pleaſant</hi> or carries with it any <hi>opinion</hi> of <hi>happineſs.</hi> In all ſuch <hi>Things</hi> I ſay there is inherent a certaine <hi>ſecret concomitant luſtre,</hi> and whiles they <hi>laſt</hi> the <hi>poſſeſſors</hi> alſo are <hi>ſubject</hi> to a <hi>Cleareneſſe</hi> and <hi>Serenitie</hi> of <hi>Mind.</hi> On the contary in all <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities</hi> there is a certaine corroding, <hi>heavie ſadneſs;</hi> for the <hi>ſpirit</hi> grieves becauſe he is <hi>Ecclips'd,</hi> and overcaſt with <hi>darkneſſe.</hi> Wee know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that <hi>povertie</hi> is but <hi>obſcuritie,</hi> and certainely in all diſaſters there is a kind of <hi>Cloud</hi> or ſomething that <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers</hi> to it. In people that are very <hi>unfortunate,</hi> this <hi>darkneſſe</hi> hath a <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> and eſpecially in the forehead there lies a notable <hi>judgement,</hi> but there are few can read in ſuch Books. Of this <hi>Virgil</hi> (who was a great <hi>Poet,</hi> but a greater <hi>Philoſopher</hi>) was not <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,</hi> for deſcribing <hi>Marcellus</hi> in the <hi>Elyſian fields,</hi> hee makes his <hi>ſad
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170666:23"/>countenance</hi> an Argument of his <hi>ſhort life.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hic Aeneas (una nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ire videbat</l>
               <l>Egregium formâ juvenem, &amp; fulgentibus Armis,</l>
               <l>Sed frons laeta parum, &amp; deiecto lumina vultu.)</l>
               <l>Quis pater, ille, virum qui ſic comitatur euntem?</l>
               <l>Eilias? anne Aliquis magnâ de ſtirpe Nepotion?</l>
               <l>Quis ſtrepitus circa Comitum? Quant vn inſtaria Ipſoeſt?</l>
               <l>Sed NOX atra Caput triſti Ctrcumvolat Vmbrâ.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But theſe are <hi>Things,</hi> that ought not to bee <hi>publickely diſcuſſed,</hi> and therefore I ſhall <hi>omit</hi> them. Hee that deſires to be <hi>happy,</hi> let him looke after <hi>Light,</hi> for it is the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe</hi> both <hi>Temporall,</hi> and <hi>Eternall.</hi> In the <hi>Houſe</hi> thereof it may bee <hi>found,</hi> and the <hi>Houſe</hi> is not farr off, nor <hi>hard</hi> to <hi>find,</hi> for the <hi>Light</hi> walks in <hi>before</hi> us, and is the <hi>guide</hi> to his owne <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> It is <hi>Light</hi> that <hi>formes</hi> the <hi>gold,</hi> and the <hi>Rubie,</hi> the <hi>Adamant</hi> and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170666:23"/>
               <hi>ſilver</hi> and he is the <hi>Artiſt</hi> that ſhapes all things. Hee that hath him, hath the Mint of <hi>Nature,</hi> and a <hi>Treaſure</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>inexhauſtible.</hi> He is bleſt with the <hi>Elect ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> and in the opinion of the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, Felix dici meretur, &amp; ſuper circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los mundi elevatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor indeed without <hi>Reaſon,</hi> for <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> her ſelfe <hi>dictates</hi> unto us, and tels us that our <hi>Happineſſe</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Light,</hi> Hence it is that we natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>love</hi> the <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>rejoyce</hi> in it, as a <hi>Thing agreeable</hi> and <hi>beneficiall</hi> unto us. On the contrarie wee <hi>feare</hi> the <hi>darkeneſſe,</hi> and are <hi>ſurpriſed</hi> in <hi>it</hi> with a certaine <hi>Horror,</hi> and a <hi>Timorous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation</hi> of ſome <hi>Hurt</hi> that may <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall</hi> us. It is <hi>Light</hi> then that wee muſt <hi>looke</hi> after, but of it ſelfe it is ſo <hi>thin</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> wee can not lay <hi>hands</hi> upon it, and make it our <hi>Poſſeſſion.</hi> We cannot <hi>confine</hi> it to any <hi>one place,</hi> that it may no more <hi>riſe,</hi> and <hi>ſet</hi> with the <hi>Sunne;</hi> wee cannot <hi>ſhut</hi> it up in a <hi>Cabinet,</hi> that we may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170666:24"/>
               <hi>uſe</hi> it when wee <hi>pleaſe,</hi> and in the darkeſt <hi>Night</hi> ſee a glorious <hi>Illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Wee muſt looke then for the <hi>Manſion</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> that <hi>oylie Aethereal ſubſtance</hi> that <hi>retaines</hi> it, for by this <hi>meanes</hi> wee may <hi>circumſcribe,</hi> and <hi>confine</hi> it. Wee may <hi>impart</hi> and <hi>communicate it</hi> to what <hi>Bodies</hi> wee pleaſe, give the <hi>baſeſt Things</hi> a moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Luſtre,</hi> and a <hi>Complexion</hi> as <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi> as the <hi>Sunne.</hi> This is that <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteric,</hi> which the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have delivered hitherto in moſt envious and obſcure <hi>Termes;</hi> and though I doe not Arrogate to my ſelfe a <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Knowledge</hi> then <hi>ſome</hi> of them <hi>had;</hi> yet I doe <hi>affirme,</hi> and that <hi>knowingly,</hi> that this <hi>Secret</hi> was never <hi>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> to the <hi>World</hi> in a Diſcourſe ſo <hi>plaine,</hi> and <hi>poſitive</hi> as <hi>this is.</hi> It is true, this <hi>Script</hi> is <hi>ſhort,</hi> and the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of <hi>Magic</hi> hath no <hi>Proportion</hi> to theſe few <hi>Lines.</hi> To write of it at <hi>large,</hi> and diſcover its <hi>Three Scenes, Elementall, Caeleſtiall,</hi> and <hi>Spirituall,</hi> was ſometimes the <hi>Deſign</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170666:24"/>of <hi>one</hi> that was able to <hi>performe.</hi> But <hi>Hee</hi> (and it was ever the <hi>Fortune</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> to be ſo <hi>ſerved</hi>) was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Oppos'd,</hi> but <hi>Abus'd</hi> by a barbarous malicious <hi>Ignorant.</hi> I ſhould thinke that <hi>Gentleman</hi> did ſet up for <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew Faire,</hi> he hath ſuch <hi>Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in his <hi>ſecond Laſh.</hi> The <hi>Tutor</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates to his <hi>Pupill,</hi> and the <hi>ſame Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pill</hi> verſifies in <hi>Commendation</hi> of his <hi>Tutor.</hi> Here was a <hi>Claw,</hi> there was never any ſo <hi>Reciprocall:</hi> Sure <hi>Rozi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> and <hi>Dapple</hi> might learne of theſe <hi>Two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is <hi>ſtuffe</hi> to <hi>ſtop</hi> our <hi>Noſes</hi> at, let us <hi>leave it</hi> for <hi>Cambridge,</hi> whence it <hi>firſt came.</hi> The <hi>Coagulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of our <hi>Water,</hi> and the <hi>Solution</hi> of our <hi>Earth,</hi> are the two greateſt and moſt difficult <hi>Operations</hi> of the <hi>Art,</hi> for theſe <hi>two</hi> are <hi>Contrarie Keyes,</hi> the <hi>Water opens,</hi> and the <hi>Earth ſhuts.</hi> Be ſure then to add nothing to the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> but what is of its <hi>owne Nature;</hi> for when it is <hi>prepared,</hi> it is <hi>al-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent:</hi> Hee coagulates <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170666:25"/>diſſolves <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> and paſſeth all the <hi>Colours:</hi> and this by vertue of its owne <hi>inward Sulphur,</hi> or <hi>Fire,</hi> which wants nothing but <hi>Excitation,</hi> or to ſpeake plainely a Simple, Naturall <hi>Coction.</hi> Every body knowes how to boyle <hi>Water</hi> in <hi>Fire;</hi> but if they knew how to boyle <hi>Fire</hi> in <hi>Water,</hi> their <hi>Phyſic</hi> would reach beyond the <hi>Kitchin.</hi> Study then, and diſpaire not, but ſtudy no <hi>Curioſities:</hi> It is a plaine ſtraight <hi>Path,</hi> that <hi>Nature</hi> walks in; and I call <hi>God</hi> to <hi>witneſſe</hi> I write not this to <hi>amaze Men,</hi> but I <hi>write</hi> that which I know to bee certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true.</p>
            <p>This is all I think fit to commnicate at this time, neither had this fallen from me, but that it was a <hi>command</hi> impos'd by my Superiors, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They that deſire <hi>experimentall knowledg,</hi> may ſtudie it as a <hi>ſure guide,</hi> but hee that <hi>reſts</hi> at his <hi>lips,</hi> and puts not his <hi>Philoſophie</hi> into his <hi>Hands,</hi> needs not theſe inſtructions: <hi>Wits Commonwealth,</hi> or a <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Apoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egms</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170666:25"/>may ſerve his turne. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe not here for <hi>any,</hi> but ſuch as <hi>looke</hi> after theſe <hi>principles,</hi> and they muſt give mee leave to <hi>inform</hi> them, if they be not perfect <hi>Maſters</hi> of the <hi>art.</hi> As for <hi>Libertie</hi> of <hi>opinion,</hi> I rob not <hi>any man</hi> of it, I am one that gives and takes, and this to avoid <hi>Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> I can ſuffer the <hi>School-man</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his owne <hi>Placets,</hi> ſo hee doth not <hi>hinder</hi> mee to follow <hi>mine.</hi> In a word, I can tolerate mens <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>pitty</hi> them: I can propound the <hi>truth,</hi> and if it bee not follow'd, it is <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to <hi>mee,</hi> That what I <hi>did</hi> was <hi>wel done.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:26"/>
            <head>A POST-SCRIPT To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmall</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>was no ſooner</hi> finiſhed <hi>(though by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) but the ſame</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie <hi>recald their</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, <hi>and now being ſomewhat</hi> transformd, I <hi>muſt (as ſome</hi> myſteriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:170666:26"/>have done) <hi>live a</hi> Tree. <hi>Yet the</hi> wiſe know, <hi>that</hi> Groves <hi>have their</hi> Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, <hi>and I remember I have read of</hi> an Image <hi>who's</hi> Hic fodias <hi>plac'd the</hi> ſubſtance <hi>in the</hi> ſhadow. <hi>To bee plain I am ſilenc'd, and though it bee in my power to</hi> ſpeake, <hi>yet I have</hi> Lawes <hi>as to this</hi> ſubject, <hi>which I muſt not</hi> trangreſſe. <hi>I have choſen therefore to oppoſe my preſent</hi> Freedom <hi>to my future</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie, <hi>and to ſpeake</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:170666:27"/>thing <hi>at this time, which I muſt never</hi> publickly ſpeak <hi>hereafter. There is no</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>in ought that I have</hi> written, <hi>if I but tell you</hi> one thing, <hi>which the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have</hi> omitted, <hi>it is that which ſome Authors have cald</hi> Vas Naturae, <hi>and</hi> Vas viride Saturni, <hi>and</hi> Miriam <hi>cals it</hi> Vas Hermetis, a menſtruous ſubſtance it is, <hi>and to ſpeak the very</hi> Truth, <hi>it is the</hi> Matrix <hi>of</hi> Nature, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you muſt place the</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal
<pb facs="tcp:170666:27"/>ſperm, <hi>aſſoone as it</hi> appears <hi>beyond its</hi> Body. <hi>The</hi> Heate <hi>of this</hi> Matrix <hi>is</hi> ſulphureous, <hi>and it is that which</hi> coagulats <hi>the</hi> ſperm, <hi>but</hi> common Fire, <hi>though it bee moſt</hi> exactly regulated, <hi>will never</hi> do it, <hi>and in this point ſee that you bee not</hi> deceived. <hi>This</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix <hi>is the</hi> life <hi>of the</hi> ſperm, <hi>for it</hi> preſerves <hi>and</hi> quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens <hi>it, but beyond the</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix <hi>it takes cold and dyes, and nothing</hi> effectual <hi>can be</hi> generated <hi>thereof, in a
<pb facs="tcp:170666:28"/>word, without this</hi> Matrix <hi>you will never</hi> coagulate <hi>the</hi> Matter, <hi>nor bring it to a</hi> minerall Complexion, <hi>and herein alſo there is a</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain meaſure <hi>to bee</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>without which you will</hi> miſcarrie <hi>in the</hi> practiſe <hi>of this</hi> Natural veſſel, ſpeaks Miriam <hi>in theſe following words.</hi> In omnibus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus eſt ſcientia, ſed Stoici propter eorum vitae brevitatem, &amp; operis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitatem hoc unicum oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultaverunt; Illi vero in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerunt
<pb facs="tcp:170666:28"/>elementa tingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; ipſi docuerunt ea, &amp; omnes Philoſophi do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent illa, praeter vas Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metis, quia illud eſt Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; ſapientia Domini Gentibus occultatum: &amp; illi qui illud ignorant neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt Regimen veritatis propter Vaſis Hermetis Ignorantiam. <hi>In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and Regiment of this thing, which they call their</hi> Veſſel, <hi>and ſometimes their</hi> Fire, <hi>conſiſts all the</hi> ſecret, <hi>and verily the</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances
<pb facs="tcp:170666:29"/>
               <hi>thereof are ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable- and ſo</hi> ſpeedy <hi>they are almoſt incredible. Had</hi> I <hi>knowne this at firſt, it had not been with mee, as it hath been, but every</hi> Event <hi>hath its</hi> time, <hi>and ſo had</hi> I. <hi>This</hi> one thing (<hi>to lay aſide other</hi> Reaſons) <hi>doth not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, but</hi> convince mee, <hi>That this</hi> Art <hi>was original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> revealed <hi>to</hi> man, <hi>for this</hi> I <hi>am ſure of, that man of</hi> himſelfe <hi>could not poſſibly think of it, for it is</hi> invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: <hi>it is removed from
<pb facs="tcp:170666:29"/>the</hi> eye, <hi>and this out of a certaine</hi> Reverence, <hi>and if by</hi> chance <hi>it comes into</hi> ſight, <hi>it</hi> withdrawes <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine</hi> naturally, <hi>for it is the</hi> ſecret <hi>of</hi> Nature, <hi>even that which the Philoſophers call</hi> primus Concubitus. <hi>This is</hi> enough <hi>to a</hi> wiſe Artiſt, <hi>at leaſt it is</hi> all I <hi>intend to publiſh, and now</hi> Reader <hi>farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:170666:30"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Felix qui potuit Rerum cognoſcere Cauſas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Metus omnes, &amp; inexorabile Fetum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Subjecit pedibus, ſtrepitum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Acherontis avari,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illum non populi Faſces, non purpura Regum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flectit, &amp; Infidos agitans diſcordia Fratres:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non Res Romana, peritura<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Regna: neque Ille</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aut doluit miſerans Inopom, aut invidit habenti.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:30"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THe</hi> neglects, and omiſſions <hi>of the</hi> Preſſe <hi>are ſo</hi> groſſe, <hi>and ſo</hi> many, <hi>that if it were not for thy ſake, more then any other</hi> conſideration, <hi>the</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>would bee aſhamed to liſt them. Bee pleaſed to correct what others have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and for meere</hi> peccadillos <hi>wee preſent them not; thou haſt here onely ſuch</hi> Errors, <hi>as may pervert thy</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>not thy</hi> candor.</p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle Dedicat. <hi>pag.</hi> 2 <hi>lin.</hi> 8, <hi>read</hi> I think it a happineſs, &amp;c. <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 3. <hi>l</hi> 4. <hi>r.</hi> Thoſe verſes, &amp;c. in the Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> I am grown in the book it ſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 11. dele kind and r. This o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>-worke, <hi>p,</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> Method. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> That it is not lawfull. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> but by a ſecret. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> to the greateſt effects. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>rea.</hi> out of his way, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170666:31"/>
            <head>Bookes Printed or ſold by <hi>VVilliam Leake,</hi> at the <hi>Crowne</hi> in Fleet-ſtret between the two Temple gates.</head>
            <p>YOrk's Heraldry. Bible of a very faire large Roman letter, 4. Orlando furioſo. <hi>Callis</hi> learned Readings on the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 23. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Cap. 5. of Sewers. <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Lawes of <hi>England. Wilkinſon</hi> office of Sheriffs. Vade mecum of a Juſtice of Peace. The booke of Feet. <hi>Perſons</hi> Law. Mirror of Juſtice. Topicks in the Laws of <hi>England. Sken</hi> de ſignificatione verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <hi>Delamans</hi> uſe of the Horizontal Quadrant. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Recreations. <hi>Welby,</hi> ſecond ſet of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, 3, 4, 5, and 6. parts. <hi>Cordarius</hi> in Engliſh. The Fort Royal of the Scriptures, or the Vade me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Concordance, Preſenting to the World above an hundred heads of Scripture, moſt of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places for publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>que uſe, the ſecond Edition much enlarged Dr. <hi>Fulks Meteors Malihus</hi> Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works. <hi>Nyrs</hi> Guanery and fire works. <hi>Cain</hi> Major, with Anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tions by <hi>Wil. Auſtin</hi> Eſquire. Mel He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liconium, by <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x. Roſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Noſce reipſum, by Sir <hi>John Davis.</hi> Annimadverſions on <hi>Lillyes</hi> Grammer. The Hiſtorie of <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Paris.</hi> The Spaniſh Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devile of Miracles Lazarille de Tormes. Chriſts Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h Annotat. by G. <hi>Sands.</hi> Hero and Leander, by <hi>Chriſtopher Marlow,</hi> and <hi>G. Chapman.</hi> Alcilia or Phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olly. Epigrams divine and moral, by Sir <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chard. Mayers</hi> Catechiſme 8, Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio Scholaſtica. Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> Sermons. <hi>Adoms</hi> on <hi>Peter.</hi> Poſing of the Accidence. Amadis de Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le. <hi>Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lliams</hi> Heraldrie. <hi>Herberts</hi> Travels. Borcas Tales. Man become guilty: by <hi>John Francis Senalt,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170666:31"/>and Enligſhed by <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of Monmoth. The Ideot in 4. books; the firſt and ſecond of Wiſedome; the 3d. of the minde; the 4. of Statick Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Ballance. The life and Reign of H. 8. written by the Lord <hi>Herbert.</hi> Cornwallis Eſſayes, and Paradoxes. Cleanards greek Grammar 8.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Playes.</label> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. Philaſter. Maids Tragedie. King and no King. The grateful Servant. The wedding The ſtrange diſcoverie. The Hollander, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ello,</hi> or the Moore of Venice. The Marchant of Venice, Tragedie of Hoffman.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
